Partial Inventory of the Robert H. Lochner Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert H. Lochner Papers
1933-2003
2007C33
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 37 digital files (0.081 GB) (2.2 linear feet)
Printed matter and photographs, relating to American radio broadcasting to Germany. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Lochner, Robert H., 1918-
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biography
1918 Born, New York
1923 Family moves to Berlin when father, Louis P. Lochner, is appointed bureau chief of Associated Press
1936 Assists father in coverage of Olympic games, then leaves Berlin to begin studies at University of Chicago
1940 Bachelor's degree, political science, University of Chicago
1941 Master's degree, economics, University of Chicago
1941-1945 Worked on German broadcasts over short-wave service, NBC radio, New York
1945 Summer Conducted studies for U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey, Germany, on effects of bombing on civilian morale
1945-1947 Director of news broadcasting for radio in the U.S. occupied zone of Germany, based in Bad Nauheim
1945-1955 Translator and interpreter for Military Governor Lucius D. Clay and High Commissioner John J. McCloy
1947-1949 Chief control officer for Radio Frankfurt
1949-1952 Editor in chief, Neue Zeitung, Frankfurt
1952-1955 Head of the press office of the American High Commission, Bonn
1954 Translator for former President Herbert Hoover on his visit to Germany
1955-1957 Head of the Information Division, U.S. Embassy, Saigon
1958-1961 Head of the European Division, Voice of America, Washington
1961 Translator for Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson during his visit to Berlin, after construction of the Berlin Wall
1961-1968 Director, RIAS (Radio in the American Sector), Berlin
1963 Translator for President John F. Kennedy during his visit to Berlin
1968-1971 Press and cultural attaché, American Embassy, Berne
1971-1996 Director, International Institute of Journalism, Berlin
1972-1989 Correspondent in Berlin for American Broadcasting Company (ABC), and Swiss News Agency
1972-1991 Berlin representative, American Chamber of Commerce in Germany
2003 Died, Berlin
Scope and Content of Collection
The Robert H. Lochner papers consist largely of photographs that Lochner saved over the years, documenting his many activities as part of the U.S. occupation forces in Germany following World War II, as translator to several high-ranking U.S. officials and dignitaries who visited Germany during the 1940s through the 1960s, and as head of the RIAS broadcast service, based in West Berlin, during the 1960s. Lochner was credited with preparing John F. Kennedy for his June 1963 trip to Germany, and at the president's request, coached him in several German phrases, including "Ich bin ein Berliner." Photos of this trip are included in this collection. Many of these photos were also used in his 2003 memoir, Ein Berliner unter dem Sternenbanner [A Berliner under the Stars and Stripes].
Arrangement
Organized into two series, Biographical File and Photographs.
Related Material
Related collections include the papers of his father, Pulitzer Prize-winning correspondent Louis Paul Lochner, which are located in several collections at the Wisconsin Historical Society Archives in Madison, the Milwaukee Public Library, and the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C. A further collection, the Louis P. Lochner family papers, is housed at the Concordia Historical Institute (Lutheran Church-Missouri Synod) in St. Louis. At the Hoover Institution Archives, a further group of documents collected by Louis P. Lochner in Germany during and following World War II is available as the Louis Paul Lochner collection.
Rundfunk im Amerikanischen Sektor (Berlin, Germany); Radio broadcasting--Germany.
- Biographical File, 1938-2003
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, 1938; memoirs, Ein Berliner unter dem Sternenbanner, 2003; and newspaper clippings, 1998-2003, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence (copies) of Louis P. Lochner, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Relates to seeking permission from Nazi party authorities for son Robert to accompany him as journalistic aide to party rally in Nürnberg
  - Memoirs, Ein Berliner Unter dem Sternenbanner, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings about Lochner, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1933-1968
  Photographic prints, originals as well as copy prints, arranged chronologically
  - Joseph Goebbels addressing gathering of the Carl Schurz Association, Berlin, 1933 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Pictured at podium with Robert Lochner
  - Robert Lochner pictured with father, Louis P. Lochner, in front of NBC radio microphone, 1942 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Lucius Clay pictured with Robert Murphy, John Foster Dulles, Robert Lochner, Bi-Zonal Economic Council, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Lucius Clay with General Brian Robertson, Bi-Zonal Economic Council, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of General Clay farewell celebration, 1949 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 8)
    General Lucius Clay with Robert Lochner, visited by Christian Stock, Erich Köhler, Hermann Pünder, at farewell gathering for Clay.
  - Photograph of General Clay at Freedom Bell dedication ceremony, 1950 October (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 9)
    General Lucius Clay with Robert Lochner, at ceremony of dedication for Freedom Bell, Schöneberg Town Hall, Berlin.
  - Photograph of Dean Acheson at ceremonial cornerstone laying, 1952 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 10)
    Dean Acheson with Robert Lochner at ceremony to lay cornerstone of Amerika Gedenkbibliothek, Berlin-Kreuzberg.
  - Photograph of Herbert Hoover on visit to Bonn, Germany, 1954 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 11)
    Herbert Hoover on visit to Germany (Bonn, Berlin), pictured with Robert Lochner, Konrad Adenauer, James Conant, Theodor Heuss, Carlo Schmidt.
  - John Foster Dulles speaking with Leopold Figl, Austrian State Treaty negotiations, with Robert Lochner, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Robert Lochner at microphone, at airport, standing with Walter Hallstein, John Foster Dulles, Ambassador James Conant, Chancellor Konrad Adenauer, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of Lyndon Johnson, US vice president, in Berlin, 1961 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 14)
    Robert Lochner with Lyndon B. Johnson, on visit to Berlin, with Willy Brandt.
  - Robert F. Kennedy with Edward M. Kennedy, visit to Berlin, with Robert Lochner, RIAS headquarters, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - John F. Kennedy, visit to Berlin, pictured in various images with Konrad Adenauer, Willy Brandt, Robert Lochner, Dean Rusk, Lucius Clay, Walter Scheel, 1963 June (Box 1, Folder 16, Reading room workstation)
    John F. Kennedy, visit to Berlin, pictured with Konrad Adenauer and Robert Lochner.
  - Robert Lochner pictured with Herbert Wehner, RIAS headquarters, Berlin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photograph of journalists meeting with Adolf Hitler, circa 1933-1936 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes Karl Von Wiegand, H. V. Kaltenborn, and Louis P. Lochner.
  - Photograph of Louis P. Lochner with Prince Louis-Ferdinand von Hohenzollern, circa late 1930s (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Golo Mann working in office at Bad Nauheim, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photograph of Ludwig Erhard and Erich Köhler, circa 1947-1948 (Reading room workstation, Box 1, Folder 21)
    Robert Lochner translating for Ludwig Erhard, Erich Köhler, Bi-Zonal Economic Council.
  - Photograph of General Lucius Clay with Stock, Lochner, and Köhler, circa 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 22, Reading room workstation)
    General Lucius Clay greeting Christian Stock, with Robert Lochner, Erich Köhler.
  - Robert Lochner with John McCloy and Dean Acheson, circa early 1950s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photograph of Robert Lochner and John Foster Dulles, circa mid 1950s (Box 1, Folder 24, Reading room workstation)
    Robert Lochner standing with John Foster Dulles, with Otto Suhr, Walther Schreiber, seated.
  - Photograph of Foreign Minister Dean Rusk and Willy Brandt, circa early 1960s (Box 1, Folder 25, Reading room workstation)
    Robert Lochner with Dean Rusk and Willy Brandt, Berlin.
  - Set of photographs, described above, digitized by donor, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Digitized photographs are available in JPG (266 ppi, 24-bit, ca. 500 KB each) and in PUB (Microsoft Office Publisher). Available on reading room workstation.
    Photographs: 01 Grundsteinlegung AGB, 02 Bonn - Conant Carlo Schmid Hoover Lochner, 03 Adenauer Kennedy Lochner Goldenes Buch Bonn, 04 Koehler Stock Lochner Clay, 05 Suhr Dulles Lochner Schreiber, 06 Abschiedsbesuch General Clay, 07 Erhard Koehler, 08 Aussenminister Rusk Brandt, 09 US-Vizepraesident Johnson in Berlin, 10 Louis P. Lochner, 11 Pastorius-Feier 1933 mit Goebbels, 12 Pastorius-Feier 1933 Goebbels am Pult, 13 Pastorius-Feier 1933 ganz rechts R.H.Lochner, 14 Clay laeutet Freiheitsglocke ein 1, 15 Clay laeutet Freiheitsglocke ein Handzeichen Lochner, 16 Louis P. Lochner mit Prince Louis Ferndinand, 17 Karl v. Wiegand H.v.Kaltenborn A-H. Louis P. Lochner, LPL mit A.H. AP-Fotos. Information on the back of the photos is also available as digitized files.
- Unprocessed papers, undated (Box 2-5)
- Declassified British government record, 1944 (Box 5)
  Formerly security-classified record of the British government, released in full. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
  - Record released in 2010, 1944; One folder containing one document (Box 5)
- Unprocessed oversize papers, undated (Box 6)